[
    {
        "question": "Can you explain the components of a closed supersonic wind tunnel and the components of an open supersonic wind tunnel?",
        "answer": "A closed supersonic wind tunnel is one in which the flow is recycled, returned, or looped through the wind tunnel. An open wind tunnel is one in which air is pulled through a vacuum on one side and exits through a vacuum pump on the opposite side. Thus, the air is never reused or returned through the tunnel. In an open wind tunnel, there is a pump that drives air into a high pressure tank at the beginning of the wind tunnel. This subsonic air then flows from the high pressure tank to the nozzle. Through the converging section of the nozzle, it speeds up until it chokes, reaching Mach 1 at the throat of the nozzle. Then, it flows through the diverging section of the nozzle, accelerating to supersonic speeds, until it reaches the test, or working section, where the area stops changing and the flow speed remains constant. The test section is where the flow conditions are designed to be steady, so the user can test their designs in a controlled environment. Then, the air goes through a converging-diverging nozzle again at the end of the tunnel. This time however the converging nozzle slows down the supersonic flow, so it once again is choked at the throat, and the flow continues to slow down as it goes through the diverging section. The flow also undergoes a series of shocks in this part of the tunnel. Finally, the flow exits the tunnel through a vacuum pump that pulls air out of the tunnel. In a closed wind tunnel, the process is similar; however, the air isn‚Äôt driven by a vacuum entrance and exit. Instead, it is looped through the tunnel. Typically, there are five important parts of a closed-circuit supersonic wind tunnel. There is the compressor, heat exchanger, nozzle, working section, and the diffuser. The flow starts by going through the nozzle. The subsonic flow speeds up in the converging section, chokes, and then continues to accelerate to supersonic speeds in the diverging section. Then, it enters the working section. In the working section, the area is constant, so the flow speed does not change. The working section is used to test models. Then, the flow enters the diffuser, which has a converging area that slows down the supersonic flow. In the diffuser, the flow experiences shocks and as a result the stagnation pressure drops. To raise the stagnation pressure back to the ideal pressure, the now subsonic flow continues through the tunnel to a compressor. The compressor does shaft work on the flow, so the pressure rises. However, the temperature also rises isentropically as shaft work is added to flow. Because of this temperature rise, a heat exchanger is added later in the tunnel before the flow returns to the nozzle to take heat out of the air to maintain a steady temperature. Then, the air reaches the nozzle, and the process begins again."
    },
    {
        "question": "Can you explain Bernoulli's equation and its applications in fluid mechanics?",
        "answer": "Bernoulli's equation describes the relationship between static pressure, velocity, and elevation in a flowing fluid. It was formulated by Daniel Bernoulli in the 18th century. The equation states that for steady, inviscid, incompressible fluids flowing along streamlines P + 1/2*rho*V^2 + rho*g*h = constant, where P is pressure, rho is density, V is velocity, g is the gravitational constant, and h is elevation. This equation can be used to determine how the velocity, elevation, or pressure change along a streamline as a result of changes in the other two variables. For example, if you measure the velocity of a flow at two points along a streamline, you can determine the change in pressure from point A to point B. However, this can only be applied along steady, inviscid, incompressible streamlines. This can be useful for pitot-static tubes, which are used to measure the pressure and velocity of the flow around an airplane, lift across airfoils, and flows through frictionless pipes. You cannot apply Bernoulli's equation across streamlines; you can only apply it along streamlines."  
    },
    {
        "question": "What is a pitot-static tube?",
        "answer": "A pitot-static tube is a device used to measure the static and stagnation pressure at a point. These devices are commonly used on aircraft to determine the static pressure, and the velocity of the airflow. The pitot-static tube works by having two openings; one faces the flow and the other is perpendicular to the flow velocity. The pitot tube that faces the flow has a stagnation point, so the local velocity is 0; therefore, the static pressure that the tube records is the stagnation pressure of the fluid. The other pressure taps experience a local velocity equal to the flow velocity, so the static pressure they record is the static pressure of the flow. Using Bernoulli's equation, these two measurements can be used to find the velocity of the flow. Po = p + 1/2*rho*v^2. Since the pitot-static tube recorded the static pressure and the stagnation pressure, the static pressure can be subtracted from the stagnation pressure to find the dynamic pressure. Then we can set the dynamic pressure equal to 1/2*rho*v^2 and solve for v to find the velocity of the flow."
    },
    {
        "question": "Explain the Steady Flow Energy Equation.",
        "answer": "The Steady Flow Energy Equation (SFEE) is a consequence of the first law of Thermodynamics, Q - W = ùö´U. It describes the conservation of energy for a steady flow process in an open system, such as a fluid flowing through a pipe or a turbine. Mathematically, it is expressed as: dQ/dt + dW/dt + dm/dt*(h + v^2/2 + gz)in = dm/dt*(h + v^2/2 + gz)out, where dQ/dt is the rate of heat transfer, dW/dt is the rate of shaft work, dm/dt is the mass flow rate, h is the specific enthalpy, v is the velocity, g is the gravitational constant, and z is the elevation. The terms in the equation represent different forms of energy per unit mass: h represents the enthalpy of the fluid, which is the sum of its internal energy and the product of pressure and specific volume, 1/2*v^2 represents the kinetic energy per unit mass of the fluid, and gz represents the potential energy per unit mass of the fluid due to its elevation. The steady flow energy equation states that the total energy per unit mass entering a control volume (inlet) is equal to the total energy per unit mass leaving the control volume (outlet), accounting for any heat transfer and work done on or by the system. The steady flow energy equation can only be used for flows that are steady, meaning they don't change over time. Thus, we don't account for a change in internal energy. To solve problems using the SFEE, find the initial specific enthalpy, velocity, and specific potential energy and then find the ending specific enthalpy, velocity, and specific potential energy. Then, find the mass flow rate. Using these quantities, you can work out the required heat and work inputs. Often, the effects of velocity and potential energy will be ignored because they are insignificant compared to the effects of the change in enthalpy."
    },
    {
        "question": "Explain the three conservation equations (mass, momentum, and energy)",
        "answer": "The three conservation equations‚Äîmass conservation, momentum conservation, and energy conservation‚Äîare fundamental principles in physics and engineering that describe the behavior of fluids and their interactions with their surroundings. The mass conservation equation, also known as the continuity equation, states that mass is conserved within a closed system or a control volume. This means the sum of the mass flow rates into and out of a control volume must be equal. Mathematically, it can be expressed as: Œ£dm/dt(in) = Œ£dm/dt(out), or Œ£rho1*v1*A1 = Œ£rho2*v2*A2 where rho1, v1, and A1 are the density, velocity, and area of the incoming flow and rho2, v2, and A2 are the density, velocity, and area of the outflowing flow. The conservation of momentum equation can best be expressed as Bernoulli‚Äôs equation in Euler‚Äôs form: p1 + rho1*v1^2 = p2 + rho2*v2^2 where p1 is the initial static pressure, rho1 is the initial density, and v1 is the initial velocity. This equation essentially states that momentum is conserved along a streamline and it can be used to relate the change in pressure to the change in velocity of fluid flows. This equation shows that the momentum of a system does not change when it is not acted upon by an outside force. The conservation of energy equation is the NSFEE energy equation. When the flow is steady and there is no heat or work input. This equation can be expressed as h1 + 1/2v2^2 + g*z1 = h2 + 1/2v2^2 + g*z2 where h is specific enthalpy, v is velocity, g is the gravitational constant, and z is the elevation. This equation shows that the energy of a system does not change when it is not acted upon by an outside force. These three equations together can be used to derive the normal shock equations and they form three fundamental laws for solving problems involving fluid flows."
    },
    {
        "question": "Can you explain how to expel a shock from the nozzle?",
        "answer": "As you decrease the exit pressure of the flow from the nozzle, the shock moves further from the throat to the end of the nozzle. If you decrease the exit pressure enough, the shock can occur after the nozzle exit. Typically if the exit pressure is higher than ambient, the shock will occur within the nozzle, if the exit pressure is lower than ambient, there will be expansion fans at the nozzle end followed by shock further downstream, and if the flow is perfectly expanded, the shocks will be minimized."
    },
    {
        "question": "Can you explain overexpanded vs underexpanded flow from nozzles?",
        "answer": "Overexpanded and underexpanded flow refer to the behavior of a fluid flow exiting a nozzle relative to the ambient conditions. In overexpanded flow, the pressure of the fluid leaving the nozzle is lower than the ambient pressure. This occurs when the exit pressure of the fluid is lower than the pressure of the surrounding environment. As a result, the flow expands further after exiting the nozzle, leading to a separation of the flow from the nozzle walls. This separation causes flow instability, shock waves, and decreased performance. Overexpanded flow is often associated with rocket nozzles operating at higher altitudes where ambient pressure is lower than at sea level. In underexpanded flow, the pressure of the fluid leaving the nozzle is higher than the ambient pressure. This occurs when the exit pressure is higher than the pressure of the surrounding environment. As a result, the flow does not fully expand to match the ambient pressure, leading to a supersonic flow at the nozzle exit. Underexpanded flow is characterized by shock waves forming at the nozzle exit, which can cause noise, vibration, and reduced efficiency. It is commonly observed in jet engine exhaust nozzles. In summary, overexpanded flow occurs when the exit pressure is too low relative to the ambient pressure, leading to flow separation and decreased performance, while underexpanded flow occurs when the exit pressure is too high relative to the ambient pressure, leading to shock waves and other issues. Both conditions can have detrimental effects on the performance and stability of the nozzle and the overall system. Perfectly expanded flow is when the exit pressure is equal to the ambient pressure. This allows for peak efficiency."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is the zeroth law necessary?",
        "answer": "The zeroth law states, If two systems are each in thermal equilibrium with a third system, then they are in thermal equilibrium with each other. The zeroth law establishes a fundamental concept: temperature. The Zeroth Law establishes the concept of temperature and the ability to compare temperatures between different systems. It provides a basis for measuring and quantifying thermal equilibrium, which is essential for understanding heat transfer processes. The Zeroth Law is essential for analyzing heat transfer processes, such as conduction, convection, and radiation. It provides a basis for understanding the direction and magnitude of heat transfer between systems based on their temperature differences. In summary, while the Zeroth Law of Thermodynamics may seem simple, its necessity lies in its establishment of the fundamental concept of temperature and its role in defining thermodynamic equilibrium, enabling temperature measurement, and facilitating the analysis of heat transfer processes."
    },  
    {
        "question": "How does the pressure change over a curved streamline?",
        "answer": "According to centripetal acceleration, we know that the acceleration of fluid moving around a curve is equal to the tangential velocity squared divided by the radius, a = -V^2/R. Further, we know that this acceleration must be driven by a pressure force, so we can say F = dp/dn*Volume. Additionally, F=ma can be re-written as F = rho*Volume*a. Therefore, combining these equations we get dp/dn*Volume = V^2/R*rho*Volume, or simplified, dp/dn = rho*V^2/R. Therefore, to find the pressure difference across curved streamlines, we can simply integrate dp = rho*V^2/R*dn from radius 1 to radius 2."
    },
       
    {
        "question": "Calculate the gauge pressure 12 m below the surface in a tank that has 10 m of water (density = 1000 kg/m^3) and 5 m of oil (density = 750 kg/m^3).",
        "answer": {
            "code": """
class Liquid:
    def __init__(self, density, depth):
        self.density = density
        self.depth = depth

liquid1 = Liquid(1000, 10)
liquid2 = Liquid(750, 5)
Fluids = [liquid1, liquid2]
desired_depth = 12
pg = 0
g = 9.81
Fluids = sorted(Fluids, key = lambda Liquid: Liquid.density)

while desired_depth > 0:
    for Fluid in Fluids:
        if Fluid.depth <= desired_depth:
            pg = pg + Fluid.depth*g*Fluid.density
            desired_depth = desired_depth - Fluid.depth
        else:
            pg = pg + desired_depth*g*Fluid.density
            desired_depth = desired_depth - desired_depth

print("The gauge pressure is", pg, "Pa")
            """,
        "explanation": "This solution takes advantage of the fact that hydrostatic pressure due to a fluid is equal to the density of the fluid times the acceleration due to gravity times the depth of the fluid. To find the pressure at a depth in a fluid we simply find the weight of the fluid above it per area. In this case, at a depth of 12 meters, we have 5 meters of oil and 7 meters of water. Therefore, p = rhowater*depthwater*g + rhooil*depthoil*g = 1000*7*9.81 + 750*5*9.81 = 105457.5 Pa."
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "Calculate the momentum flux of a fluid moving through a cylinder of radius R, with a velocity profile v(r) = Vo(1-(r/R)^2) where R = 1 m, density = 1000 kg/m^3, and Vo = 10 m/s.",
        "answer": {
            "code": """
import math

R = 1
rho = 1000
Vo = 10

flux = math.pi/3*rho*(Vo**2)*R**2

print("The momentum flux is", flux, "kg*m/s^2")

            """,
        "explanation": "Momentum flux is equal to the integral of density times velocity squared times the area. In this case we can write v(r) = Vo(1-(r/R)^2) and da = 2*pi*r*dr and rho = 1000 kg/m^3 where Vo = 10 m/s and R = 1m. Solving the integral from r=0 to r=R of (Vo(1-(r/R)^2))^2*rho*2*pi*r*dr, we get pi/3*rho*Vo^2*R^2 = pi/3*1000*10^2*1 = 104.72 kN."
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "An engine takes heat from a thermal reservoir at a rate of 2 kW at 102 degrees Celsius and from a cold place at 12 degrees Celsius and rejects heat to the environment at 30 degrees Celsius. Determine the minimum rate of heat transfer from the cold space.",
        "answer": {
            "code": """
Q1 = 2
T1 = 102
T2 = 12
T3 = 30

T1 = T1 + 273.15
T2 = T2 + 273.15
T3 = T3 + 273.15

Q2 = (T3*T2)/(T2-T3) * (Q1/T1 - Q1/T3)

print("The minimum rate of heat transfer from the cold place is ", Q2, " kW")

            """,
        "explanation": "In order to solve problems involving heat transfer in 3 body systems, we can use Clausius inequality and conservation of energy. First by conservation of energy we know that Q1 + Q2 + Q3 = 0. Therefore we can say that Q3 = -(Q1 + Q2). Next, the Clausius inequality tells us that Q1/T1 + Q2/T2 + Q3/T3 <= 0. Substituting for Q3, we get Q1/T1 + Q2/T2 -(Q1 + Q2)/T3 <=0. Substituting Q1 = 2 kW, T1 = 375.15 K, T2 = 285.15 K, T3 = 303.15 K, the maximum Q2 is 6.08 kW."
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "Air flows steadily through a converging-diverging nozzle. The area at the throat of the nozzle (where the flow is choked) is 1/2 the inlet area. Determine the Mach number at the inlet of the nozzle. Plot the Mach number as the area changes from inlet to throat.",
        "answer": {
            "code": """
import numpy
import matplotlib.pyplot as pl

M2 = 1

Ms = []
for i in range(1, 101):
    Ms.append(i/100)

#I ran a linear regression to find non-dimensional mass flow rate as a function of Mach Number. The result was the polynomial ndm(M) = 6.53763187e-01(M^4) + -1.64823282e+00(M^3) + 6.70739635e-02(M^2) + 2.20868819e+00(M) + 6.33202794e-05
def M2Ndm(M):
    return 6.53763187e-01*M**4 + -1.64823282e+00*M**3 + 6.70739635e-02*M**2 + 2.20868819e+00*M + 6.33202794e-05

ndms = []
for M in Ms:
    ndms.append(M2Ndm(M))

ndm2 = M2Ndm(M2)
Aratio = .5

ndm1 = ndm2*Aratio

arr = numpy.polyfit(ndms, Ms, 7)
def Ndm2M(ndm):
    return arr[0]*ndm**7 + arr[1]*ndm**6 + arr[2]*ndm**5 + arr[3]*ndm**4 + arr[4]*ndm**3 + arr[5]*ndm**2 + arr[6]*ndm + arr[7]

M1 = Ndm2M(ndm1)

print("The input Mach number at the inlet is", M1)

fig, ax = pl.subplots()
As = []
A2 = 1
relndms = []
for ndm in ndms:
    if ndm > ndm1:
    relndms.append(ndm)

relMs = []
for M in Ms:
    if M > M1:
    relMs.append(M)

for ndm in relndms:
    As.append(ndm2/ndm*A2)

ax.plot(As, relMs)
ax.set_xlabel("Area Ratio")
ax.set_ylabel("Mach Number")
ax.set_title("Mach Number vs Area Ratio")
ax.text(As[0],M1,"inlet")
ax.text(1,M2,"throat")

            """,
        "explanation": "To solve this problem, we use the gas flow properties tables. First, we use the table to find the non-dimensional mass flow rate at the throat where we know the mach number is 1. Looking at the table, we see that the non-dimensional mass flow rate is 1.2810 when the Mach number is 1. In this code, I use a regression fit model to find mach number from non-dimensional mass flow rate and vice versa created from the data in the table. Then we use the area ratio from throat to inlet to find the non-dimensional mass flow rate at the inlet. We know that the stagnation pressure is constant in the converging section of the nozzle and Cp, To, and mdot are constant as well, therefore we can take mdot*sqrt(Cp*To)/(Athroat*Po) = 1.2810 and multiply by Athroat/Ainlet to find the non-dimensional mass flow rate at the inlet. 1.2810 * 1/2 = .6405, so the non-dimensional mass flow rate at the inlet is .6405. Looking at the table, the corresponding mach number is around .304. I also included a plot to show how the mach number changes as the area changes from throat to inlet."
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "Air driven by a fan flows through a frictionless pipe from station A to station B. After reaching station B, the air flows through a curved section of pipe with an inner radius of 5 m and outer radius of 10 m. At station A, the velocity is 20 m/s and the pressure is 20 Pa. At station B, the velocity is 15 m/s. Assuming the air enters the curved section with uniform velocity and pressure, what is the pressure of the air on the outside of the curve as the air exits the bend? The density of air is 1.225 kg/m^3.",
        "answer": {
            "code": """
import math

v1 = 20
p1 = 20
v2 = 15
rho = 1.225
R2 = 10
R1 = 5

p2 = p1 + .5*rho*(v1**2 - v2**2)

deltaP = rho*(v2**2)*math.log(R2/R1)

final_pressure = p2 + deltaP

print("the pressure is", final_pressure, "Pa")

            """,
        "explanation": "To solve this problem we first find the pressure at station B using Bernoulli's equation and then we use the equation to find the change in pressure across curved streamlines. Bernoulli's equation tells us that p1 + 1/2*rho*v1^2 = p2 + 1/2*rho*v2^2 where p1 and v1 are the pressure and velocity at station A and p2 and v2 are the pressure and velocity at station B. Solving this for p2 with the values given v1 = 20 m/s, p1 = 20 Pa, rho = 1.225 kg/m^3, and v2 = 15 m/3, we find that p2 = 127 Pa. Next we find the pressure change across the curved section of the tube. To do this, we use the equation dp/dn = p*V^2/R and we integrate p*V^2/(R+n)dn to find the change in pressure from the inside to the outside of the curve. Then, we add this change in pressure to the pressure at station B, to find the pressure on the outside of the curve. This change is approximately 191 Pa, so the pressure on the outside of the curve is around 318 Pa."
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "A piston-cylinder device contains 0.5 kg of air at an initial pressure of 200 kPa and a volume of 0.1 m^3. The air undergoes an isothermal compression process to a final volume of 0.05 m^3. Calculate the final pressure of the air if the temperature remains constant at 300 K. Plot the pressure vs volume diagram for this process.",
        "answer": {
            "code": """
import matplotlib.pyplot as pl

p1 = 200
v1 = .1
v2 = .05

p2 = (p1*v1)/v2

print("The final pressure is", p2, "kPa")

vs = []
ps = []
vi = v1*1000
vf = v2*1000
for v in range(int(vi),int(vf)):
    v = v/1000
    vs.append(v)
    p = p1*v1/v
    ps.append(p)

fig, ax = pl.subplots()
ax.plot(ps, vs)
ax.set_xlabel("pressure")
ax.set_ylabel("volume")
ax.set_title("pressure vs volume")
ax.text(p1,v1,"A")
ax.text(p2,v2,"B")

            """,
        "explanation": "This solution relies on the ideal gas law, PV = nRT. Because temperature in this process is constant, R is constant, and the amount of gas is constant, nRT is constant. Therefore, p1v1 = p2v2 because p1v1 = nRT and p2v2 = nRT. Substituting v1 = .1 m^3 and p1 = 200 kPa into the equation we find that pv = 20 kPa*m^3 for the duration of the process. We can plot p = 20/v from vi = .1 m^3 to vf = .05 m^3 to give a pressure vs volume diagram for this process. At vf = .05 m^3, p = 20/.05 = 400 kPa."
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "Air is flowing across steady, incompressible, streamlines. The pressure measured at station A is 200 kPa, and the pressure measured at station B is 100 kPa. Calculate the change in specific kinetic energy from station A to B.",
        "answer": {
            "code": """
            p1 = 200
            p2 = 100

            KEChange = p1 - p2

            print("The change in specific KE from station A to station B is", KEChange, "kJ/m^3")
            """,
        "explanation": "This solution uses Bernoulli's Equation, p1 + 1/2*rho*v1^2 = p2 + 1/2*rho*v2^2. Rearranging, we find that p1 - p2 = 1/2*rho(v2^2 - v1^2). Recognizing that 1/2*rho*(v2^2-v1^2) = the change in specific KE, we recognize that the change is equal to the pressure at station A, p1, minus the pressure at station B, p2. In this case, the change in specific KE is 200 kPa - 100 kPa = 100 kJ/m^3."
        }
    }
]





